Guide to the George H. Seeley Papers and Photographs
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George H. Seeley papers and photographs
1900-1975
1900-1950
YCAL MSS 459
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.94
(23 boxes)
This collection consists chiefly of papers and photographs created and collected by George H. Seeley that document his photographic career, as well as his later life and family spanning from 1900 to 1975. The collection includes glass plate negatives used by Seeley to create his professional photographs. Photographic prints in the collection are predominantly work prints created by Seeley. There are also film negatives that document his later life and family, as well as the landscape around Stockbridge and at Cape Cod.
Seeley, George H., 1880-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marion Cady Davis Byron, 1975.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 8-17 (glass negatives): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Boxes 19-21 (glass transparencies): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Boxes 22-23 (film negatives): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
George H. Seeley (1880-1955)
George Henry Seeley (1880-1955) was a photographer. He was a lifetime resident of Stockbridge, Massachusetts and supervisor of the art instruction for local schools, as well as an amateur ornithologist. As a photographer, Seeley was a leading member of the Photo-Secession movement along with Alfred Stieglitz, Clarence White, and others. Related to this work, he wrote articles about photography and published his photographs in photographic journals, including Camera Work, as well as exhibiting his images around the world. Seeley frequently used his sisters, May Elizabeth Seeley (born 1878), Lilian R. Seeley (born 1884), and Laura S. Seeley (1888-1979), as models for his photographs. His photography emphasizes soft focuses and subtle tonality. Seeley is also known for his landscape photography of winters in New England and Cape Cod beachscapes.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists chiefly of papers and photographs created and collected by George H. Seeley that document his photographic career, as well as his later life and family spanning from 1900 to 1975.
A strength of the collection is the glass plate negatives used by Seeley to create his professional photographs. Photographic prints in the collection are predominantly work prints created by Seeley. There are film negatives that document his later life and family, as well as the landscape around Stockbridge and at Cape Cod.
A scrapbook in the collection, 1900-1915, includes correspondence with Alfred Stieglitz and Clarence White, as well as Curtis Bell, Alvin Langdon Coburn, Wendell G. Corthell, Daniel Chester French, Spencer Kellogg, Jr., John Nilsen Laurvik, Philip P. Sharples, and Edward Steichen. There is also loose correspondence with many of the same people, circa 1900-1930, as well as John Burroughs, Adolph de Meyer, Edward R. Dickson, and Augustus Thibaudeau. Writings in the collection include a set of index cards with notes relating to his photography and a notebook with entries about birds, as well as drafts by Laura Seeley about art photography and her brother. Realia in the collection consists of medals and awards for his photography, 1905-1930, as well as a register for an exhibit of Seeley's photographs in New York City, circa 1915-1918.
A small quantity of correspondence in the collection documents communication between his sister, Laura Seeley and Robert M. Doty of the George Eastman House, as well as with staff at the Yale University Library, circa 1960.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Papers, 1900-1975. II. Photographs, 1900-1950. III. Negatives and Glass Transparencies, circa 1900-1940.
Photographers -- Massachusetts; Photography, Artistic; Cape Cod (Mass.) -- Pictorial works; Stockbridge (Mass.) -- Pictorial works; Gelatin dry plate negatives; Gelatin silver negatives; Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Platinum prints; Bell, Curtis; Burroughs, John, 1837-1921; Coburn, Alvin Langdon, 1882-1966; Corthell, Wendell G.; Davis, May Elizabeth Seeley, 1878-; De Meyer, Adolf, Baron, 1868-1949; Dickson, Edward R. (Edward Robert), 1880-1922; Doty, Robert M.; French, Daniel Chester, 1850-1931; Kellogg, Spencer, Jr., 1876-1944; Laurvik, J. Nilsen (John Nilsen), 1877-; Seeley, George H., 1880-1955; Seeley, Laura S., 1888-1979; Seeley, Lilian R., 1884-; Sharples, Philip P. (Philip Price); Steichen, Edward, 1879-1973; Stieglitz, Alfred, 1864-1946; Thibaudeau, Augustus Jackson, 1866-1939; White, Clarence H., 1871-1925
- Papers, 1900-1975; Series I; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers and Material.
  Scope and Contents
  This series chiefly consists of correspondence written to Seeley, as well as examples of his writing and collected material. A scrapbook in in the subseries Other Papers and Material also includes correspondence
  - Correspondence
    Arranged alphabetically by name.
    - Anderson, Paul L., 1913? December 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Boston Art Club, 1920 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Invitation by James Fortescue, Jr.
    - Buergel Goodwin, Heinrich, 1923 September-October 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Burroughs, John, 1911 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes a note from "Baky."
    - Butler, Norman F., 1911 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Camera Club of New York, 1921 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Letter by Floyd Vail.
    - Choate, Mabel, 1911? October 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Coburn, Alvin Langdon, 1906 August 7-1907 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Country Life in America, 1916 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Letter written by Henry Hodgman Saylor.
    - de Meyer, Adolph, 1913 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Dickson, Edward R., 1911 April 11-1915 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Doty, Robert M., 1959 August 13-1961 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Letters to Laura Seeley. Includes a postcard also signed by Alvin Langdon Coburn.
    - Ellis, Rosalie J., 1955 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Letter to Laura Seeley.
    - Ewel, Otto, 1908 July 1-1909 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Forbush, Edward Howe, 1920 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - French, Wilfred A., 1911 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Hofmann, Julius, circa 1904 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Letter to Dr. Robert Reininger.
    - International Photography Exhibition, Gothenburg, Sweden, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Biographical/Historical note
      Exhibition sponsored by the Göteborgs Handels - och Sjöfartstidning [ Gothenburg Trade and Shipping Gazette ] newspaper.
      Includes a draft letter by George H. Seeley.
    - Laine, Edmund Randolph, 1943 December 17-1944 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Laurel Hill Association, 1944 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Invitation by Alice McBurney Riggs, secretary of the association.
    - Lindblom, Andreas, 1929 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - New York Times, 1914 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Letter written by Seymour Eaton.
    - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1933 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Letter written by Philip N. Yountz.
    - Pope, Eric, 1919 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - La Revue moderne des arts et de la vie, 1929 December 2-1930 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes a draft manuscript by critic G. de Cordis, ""Il fut un temps.. .," which reviews the exhibit by Seeley at the International Photography Exhibition, Gothenburg, Sweden, as well as English translations by Laura Seeley.
    - Seeley, George H.
      Letters and draft letters written by George H. Seeley.
      - Laurel Hill Association, circa 1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        Draft letter.
      - Seeley, Laura, 1900 October 20-1907 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Seeley family, 1910 November 5-1911 March 2, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
        Eight postcards to members of the Seeley family.
      - ----, Walter, 1944 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Seeley, Laura, circa 1960
      Letters and draft letters written by Laura Seeley.
      - Byron, Marion Davis, 1975 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Doty, Robert M., circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Seeley, George H., 1912 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 32)
        General note
        NOS, 20110401
    - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1907 January 9-1910 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Struss Pictorial Lens, 1916 November 9-18 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Letters by Karl Struss
    - Thibaudeau, Augustus, 1915 April 28-May 8 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - White, Clarence H., 1910 April 25-May 7 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Yale University Library
      Letters from staff of the Yale University Library to Laura Seeley.
      - Babb, James T., 1960 July 8 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Gallup, Donald C., 1960 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - ----, Helena D., 1955 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - ----, Marsha, 1960 August 5 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Envelopes, 1906-1959 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Envelopes, some from corporate bodies, including George Eastman House, Fiera di Milano, and Société de photographie de Marseille.
  - Writings
    - By George H. Seeley
      - Notebook with notes about birds, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Index Cards on photographic processes, circa 1925-1935 (Box 2)
      - Memorandum book, 1939-1948 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - By Laura Seeley
      - "American Painting and Photography", 1916 November-December (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Notes about George H. Seeley, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 45)
        Prepared for Weston Naef of the Metropolitan Museum
    - By Others
      - Hyman, F. S., Jr., Poems, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 46-48)
      - Unidentified, Sketchbook, 1938 November (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Other Papers and Material
    - Scrapbook, 1900-1915 (Box 3)
      Scrapbook compiled by Seeley that includes correspondence, exhibition catalogs, tear sheets, and newspaper clippings.
      Scattered correspondence, 1904-1913, includes letters from Curtis Bell, Alvin Langdon Coburn, Wendell G. Corthell, Daniel Chester French, Spencer Kellogg, Jr., John Nilsen Laurvik, Philip P. Sharples, Edward Steichen, Alfred Stieglitz, and Clarence H. White, as well as the Société de photographie de Marseille. There is also a poem dedicated to Seeley by Frederick Henry Koch in 1909.
      The scrapbook includes catalogs and newspaper clippings related to exhibitions of Seeley's photographs, 1905-1915. These include shows at the Albright Art Gallery, Galleries of the Art Association of Montreal, Montross Gallery, National Arts Club, Photographic Society of Philadelphia, Photo-Succession Galleries, Print Gallery, and Utica Public Library, as well as shows at his home. A catalog for an exhibition at the Free Public Library of Newark in 1911 is accompanied by photographs of the show.
      Tear sheets of photographic reproductions and articles about Seeley, 1900-1914, derive from several publications, including Academy Notes, American Photography, The Camera, The Craftsman, The International Studio, Photo Era, The Photographer, Western Camera Notes, and Wilson's Photographic Magazine.
    - Exhibit Label for Photograph Landscape at the Panama-Pacific International Exposition, San Francisco, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Register for a Gallery Exhibit in New York City, circa 1915-1918 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      Includes signatures for attendees, including Laura Gilpin, Walter Eben Nettleton, and Augustus Thibaudeau.
    - Willo Visible Dodger for Controlled Projection Prints, circa 1938 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Group studio portrait of six women and six men, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Awards
      - Photo Club Budapest, Bronze Medal, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Société de photographie de Marseille, Salon 1905, Gold Medal (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Wiener Photo-Klub (Vienna Photo Club), VII. Exhibition, Bronze Medal, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - All Japan Societies in the Asahi Shimbun, Tokyo and Osaka, Fourth International Photographic Salon of Japan, Silver Medal, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Photographs, 1900-1950; Series II; 0.84; (3 boxes)
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Photographic Prints, Photograph Album, and Family Photographs and Photographs by Others.
  This series chiefly consists of artistic and family photographs created by Seeley. The photographic prints may derive from negatives in Series III, but no effort was made to match prints to negatives during processing the collection.
  - Photographic Prints, circa 1900-1915; circa 140 photographic prints (Box 5)
    Chiefly work platinum prints of art photographs created Seeley. Many of the images depict his sisters, May Elizabeth Seeley, Lilian R. Seeley, and Laura S. Seeley as allegorical figures. A portion of the prints depict male figures, including several portraits of an African American man. Landscape views in the subseries depict farms, ponds, streams, and woodland scenes. There is also a small quantity of still lifes.
  - Photograph Album, circa 1910-1915; 35 photographic prints (Box 6)
    Album with contact gelatin silver prints from glass plate negatives. Images principally consist of portraits of Seeley's sisters, as well as landscape views and still lifes.
  - Family Photographs and Photographs by Others, circa 1910-1950; circa 40 photographic prints (Box 7)
    This subseries principally includes informal family photographs that depict Seeley, his sisters, and his extended family, including his brother-in-law, Winthrop Isham Davis (1870-1957), and niece, Marion Cady Davis Byron (1910-1988).
    Photographs by other photographers include a portrait of Frederick H. Koch created in 1908 by John H. Lorenz of Boston, Massachusetts, and inscribed to Seeley by Koch; a view of the rostrum on Laurel Hill in Stockbridge, Massachusetts, by F. S. Hyman, Jr., circa 1945; and a studio portrait of an unidentified group of men and women, circa 1905.
- Negatives and Glass Transparencies, circa 1900-1940; Series III; 5.64; (16 boxes)
  Series III is organized into three subseries: Glass Negatives, Glass Transparencies, and Film Negatives.
  This series chiefly consists of artistic and family photographs created by Seeley. The negatives may be the source for photographic prints in Series II, but no effort was made to match prints to negatives during processing the collection.
  Many of the images on the glass negatives and transparencies depict his sisters, May Elizabeth Seeley, Lilian R. Seeley, and Laura S. Seeley as allegorical figures, as well as images of of male figures. Landscape views in the subseries depict farms, ponds, streams, woodland scenes, and beachscapes. There is also a number of still lifes.
  - Glass Negatives, circa 1900-1915; 263 negatives (Box 8–17)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Wooden negative boxes, circa 1915 (Box 18)
    A sample set of two boxes that originally housed the glass negatives.
  - Glass Transparencies, circa 1900-1915; 52 transparencies (Box 19–21)
  - Film Negatives, circa 1930-1940; circa 420 negatives (Box 22–23)
    Nitrate film negatives of photographic images created by Seeley that chiefly document natural and built landscapes, probably surrounding Stockbridge and Cape Cod, Massachusetts, as well as informal images of his family and animals, including cows, ducks, and wild birds.